## SHABBER HUSSAIN, MD

shabber.hussain@gmail.com

LinkedIn: www.linkedin.com/in/shabberhussain



Cell: (413) 749-2434

## **DOCTOR**

A highly personable, dependable and reliable caregiver with experience in Medicine and Surgery seeks a healthcare position in your department. Multilingual and adaptable to new cultures. Extensive exposure of 'primary-care' health issues and familiarity with health determinants from a global perspective. Acceptable to relocate.

#### SPECIFIC STRENGTHS

- Holistic Approach to Patient Care, acquired from a background in Medicine and Surgery.
- Apt Diagnostic Skills and Management Planning.
- Excellent Patient Rapport and Outstanding Bedside Manners strong interpersonal and relationship building skills.
- Sound Ethical Values good understanding of the principles concerning Physician-Patient Relationship, and issues of Medical Malpractice.
- Methodical and Meticulous from application of an in-depth understanding of basic medical sciences and core clinical concepts.
- Team Player who works in harmony with medical staff, administration, patient, and family members to ensure high quality medical attention.

#### PROFESSIONAL EDUCATION

USMLE® Step 3 Federation of State Medical Boards (FSMB), USA	2016
Doctor of Medicine (MD) ECFMG Certificate Educational Commission for Foreign Medical Graduates (ECFMG®), USA	2015
USMLE® Step 2 Clinical Skills Educational Commission for Foreign Medical Graduates (ECFMG®), USA	2015
SCHS General Practice Saudi Commission for Health Specialties (SCHS), KSA	2013
AMC MCQ CAT Australian Medical Council (AMC) Limited, Australia	2011
USMLE® Step 2 Clinical Knowledge Educational Commission for Foreign Medical Graduates (ECFMG®), USA	2009

USMLE® Step 1
Educational Commission for Foreign Medical Graduates (ECFMG®), USA

Bachelor of Medicine and Bachelor of Surgery (MB BS)
Punjab Medical College Faisalabad, (University of Health Sciences Lahore),
Pakistan

#### MISCELLANEOUS EDUCATION

**CMEs Ongoing** Workshops, lectures/ presentations, rounds/ grand rounds, journal clubs, M&M, multidisciplinary meetings, teaching sessions, and discussion forums. 2014 **Basic Life Support (BLS) Skills**  Current License: April, 2014 – April, 2016 Previous License: February 2012 – February 2014 2014 **Critical Care** Certificate No. TC-AR-CC-1021 (dated January 2, 2014) **Ongoing Quality Assurance** Maintain excellent standing with the Quality Control Department. **Ongoing Infection Control Assurance** Maintain excellent standing with the Infection Control Department. 2012 **Infection Control Workshop** Completed mandated training, as per employment requirement. 2012 **External & Internal Disaster Management** Completed mandated drill as per employment requirement. 2010 **IELTS (Academic)** Overall Band Score: 7.0; Speaking/Listening: 7.5

#### **EXPERIENCE**

General Medical Officer/ General Physician Akram Medical Complex (Pvt) Ltd, Lahore, Pakistan (PK)

December 2014 to June 2016

- A tertiary care hospital with well-developed surgery, medical, ICU, accident & emergency (A&E) departments, including subspecialties. Has a fully equipped ambulance service.
- Provided comprehensive and holistic patient care dealing with outpatients/ inpatients, intensive care as well as emergency. My rotations in the 7-beds ICU allowed opportunities to deal with critical conditions. The minor OR integrated with A&E allowed me to quickly manage patients requiring

- minor procedures. Transitional shortage in the 4-fully dedicated OR gave me a chance to perform as surgical first assistant for 2 months.
- The well-renowned Prof. Dr. Javed Akram, Vice Chancellor of Pakistan Institute of Medical Sciences is a visiting consultant providing consultation services in the Medical OPD. Running twice a week his OPD days were the busiest, seeing the highest number of patients from all segments. For me it has been a privilege to have assisted Prof. Akram on his OPD days, in addition to my other responsibilities.

### General Practitioner/ Volunteer Chohan Hospital Sundar, PK

November 2014 to June 2016

- I started by volunteering my time following my regular job to do community service at the Chohan Hospital Sundar. On an average, I would volunteer 2 to 3 days a week, including my off days. This continued for 10-months, until by end of August 2015 the hospital management asked me to accept the formal position of a general practitioner in the hospital.
- The Chohan Hospital Sundar is a personal initiative of Dr. Gulzar Qasim to establish it as a secondary care rural hospital in his hometown of Sundar. The hospital serves to furnish a variety of healthcare facilities for the farming community of Sundar, but at a nominal basic fee. My decision to volunteer for free, was a way to support this noble cause.
- I took personal initiative in supporting both medical and surgical services and routinely assisted the general surgeons as the surgical first assistant in a variety of GI and thyroid surgeries.

## Extern in Internal Medicine/ Palliative Care Private Group Practice of Shoaib Hashmi, MD, Baltimore, MD, USA

August 2015 to August 2015

- Group practice led by Dr. Shoaib A. Hashmi, MD. Services at the group include both internal medicine as well as palliative care.
- The 9-to-5-clinic shift afforded a chance to shadow Dr. Hashmi as he saw patients in his office. Every evening, following his day shift, Dr. Hashmi would take me to see patients admitted under his care in the many nursing homes/ assisted living facilities that he frequents. Over there, I would assist him in updating medical records while we provided follow-up care for his patients and in helping prepare files for the newly admitted patients, until late in the night. This shadowing opportunity was of one-week in duration.

### Observer in Epilepsy Research Kaminski/ Koubeissi Lab, The George Washington University, Washington, DC, USA

June 2015 to July 2015

- Observed the following procedures:
- Operant Conditioning (positive reinforcement) of Sprague Dawley rats, in the Operant Conditioning Chamber (Skinner Box).
- Kainic Acid Model of Temporal Lobe Epilepsy: Induction of status epilepticus in male Sprague-Dawley rats treated with Inj. Kainic acid (5 mg/kg/hr., intraperitoneal), until class IV/V seizures for >3 hrs.
- Kindling Model: Induction of self-sustained status epilepticus by electrical stimulation of the Amygdala (Kindling) in male Sprague-Dawley rats (modified from Nissinen et al. 2000).
- Low-Frequency Stimulation (LFS) of Area Tempestas and Claustrum: Continuous bilateral LFS (1 Hz for 24 hrs. /7 days a week) up to 2 wks. in either the Area Tempestas or the Claustrum.
- Electrophysiology-Video Monitoring in Rats: Animals are continuously monitored for 24 hrs. every 3-4 days for 2 wks.
- Transcardial Perfusion and Cardiac Puncture of Rats: Following perfusion, the brain is dissected and

- placed in vials with the fixative. Post-fixing done for 2 hrs. or overnight, before proceeding to tissue processing.
- Followed lab safety protocols regarding Personal Protective Equipment (PPE), aerosols handling, disinfection /decontamination, sharps handling and containers & labeling.

## Extern in Cardiovascular Practice Dearborn & Detroit Clinics, ARK Medical Center, MI, USA

April 2015 to June 2015

- A Joint-Cardiovascular Practice run by three interventional cardiologists.
- The Dearborn Clinic caters to the largely Arab community of Dearborn, MI.
- The Detroit Clinic is housed within the DMC Harper-Hutzel Hospital (Harper University Hospital), Detroit, MI.
- Interaction with a mix of African-American, American and Middle Eastern patients/ staff.
- Assisted in patient data gathering for paper records/ EMR.
- Provided Arabic interpretation for certain patients.

# General Physician/ Emergency Medicine Physician Ministry of Health (MOH), Riyadh, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia (KSA)

October 2011 to September 2014

- Completed 3-annual contracts (lunar/Hijri calendar).
- Licensed as General Practitioner with the Saudi Commission for Health Specialties (License No.: 13-R-M-0018139).
- Term spent at MOH affiliated hospitals --- the Ar'ar Central Hospital as well as the Prince Abdulaziz Bin Musa'ad Hospital, as below.

## General Physician (Licensed as General Practitioner with SCHS) Ar'ar Central Hospital, MOH, KSA

October 2012 to September 2014

- Flexible team player, with multitude of skills and an ability to cope with the changing environment.
- Certain shifts required covering for hospital floors in addition to ED duties. Liaised with many departments.
- Dealt with a multitude of non-acute and sub-acute illnesses, as well as seeing patients during acute stages of disease.
- Adeptly carried out stabilization of critical cases in the 24-beds emergency ICU.
- Dealt with medico-legal cases, collecting samples, preparing reports and maintaining chain of custody.
- Engaged in professional development for continuing competence.
- Contributed to clinical audit by preparing organized record.
- Acquired Arabic language and cultural skills.
- Rotations include the following:
  - Emergency
  - Surgery On-Call (in Emergency)
  - o Medical On-Call (in Emergency)
  - o ICU

- Effective time and people management. Handled high patient turnover (approx. 50 consultations/shift).
- Administered appropriate stabilization of the severely ill and unstable patients.
- Engaged in a busy on-call involving a 1:3 Rolling Rota.
- Directed the triage, ensuring rapid differentiation of illnesses by acuity and severity.
- Participated with the Code Team, Rapid Response Team and Forward Aid Team.
- Communicated with the ED directors regarding calls covered.
- Assured backup at times of staff shortage.
- Implemented quality criteria by CBAHI standard.
- Record entry using Health Insights MedicaPlus® EMR.
- Rotations include the following:
  - o Emergency
  - o Neurosurgery
  - Surgery
  - o Medical

## Travels, Examinations, Professional Registrations, Licenses and Board requirements

July 2010 to September 2011

- Travel to Australia; emigration to Saudi Arabia.
- Obtained IELTS and AMC qualifications leading to accreditation with the Medical Board of Australia.
- Habitation and acculturation in Australia; completed State Medical registration requirements for supervised practice as medical practitioner.
- Appeared for job interviews, fulfilled various visa procedures and obtained requirements for professional licenses.
- Satisfied job requirements for the Ministry of Health, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia
- Completed requirements for emigration to Saudi Arabia, etc.

### Medical Officer in Cardiothoracic Surgery & Cardiac ICU Gulab Devi Chest Hospital & Postgraduate Medical Institute Lahore, PK

April 2010 to June 2010

- Learned skills for mechanical and pharmacological interventions in the ICU.
- Directed ventilator support along with monitoring.
- Rendered effective postoperative care in the 9-bed High-Dependency Unit for patients with thoracic surgeries and occasionally for the ICU step-down patients.
- Engaged in joint cardiology and cardiothoracic surgery didactic sessions.

# Assistant Physician in General/ Community Practice Syed Clinic (Pvt.) Ltd., Lahore, PK

February 2007 to February 2010

- An interesting case mix broadened the scope of practice.
- Coordinated care between ambulatory settings, hospitals and homes.
- Skill in intra-family dynamics/ domiciliary care.

- Implemented the practice's EMR, spurred by an interest in healthcare IT, using the OneNote EMR Add-on.
- Employed preventative practices in managing chronic diseases.

## Senior House Officer in Neurosurgery Shaikh Zayed Federal Postgraduate Medical Institute Lahore, PK

December 2005 to December 2006

- Expeditious handling of critical emergencies involving head trauma.
- Adapted with neuronavigation techniques that utilize stereotactic brain surgery and biopsies with the help of MEDTRONIC STEALTHSTATION®.
- Supported care of patients in the 14-bed Neuro ICU for traumatic brain and spine injury, subarachnoid and intracerebral hemorrhage, aneurysms and neurological disorders.
- Effectively liaised with several departments to expedite care. This interdisciplinary collaboration realized a reduction in time needed for CT scans in life-threatening emergencies.

## Senior House Officer in General Surgery Shaikh Zayed Federal Postgraduate Medical Institute Lahore, PK

April 2005 to October 2005

- This high volume center for GI diseases provided ample learning of GI surgery.
- Abundant involvement with pancreatic diseases. The program in pancreatic diseases is one of the major in the area, with approximately 30 pancreatic resections performed annually.
- Interdisciplinary collaboration at weekly service conference enhanced patient management by the multidisciplinary perspective.
- Contributed to research in liaison with senior faculty. Was instrumental in providing a source of patients and clinical ideas.
- Pursued proficiency in surgical handicraft at the bi-weekly theatre sessions.
- Participated in academic activities such as the Morbidity and Mortality (M&M), GI Multidisciplinary Conferences, GI Surgery Conferences, Journal Club and the PowerPoint Teaching Conferences.

### House Surgeon Services Hospital Lahore, PK

February 2005 to April 2005

- Acquired understanding of surgical concepts and ability in handling trauma.
- Gained manual dexterity in essential surgical craft under the guidance of senior staff.
- Ample pediatric exposure in addition to adult patients.
- Quickly adapted to the surgical culture and advanced to senior house officer, at the Shaikh Zayed Federal Postgraduate Medical Institute, Lahore (next).

### House Physician Jinnah Hospital Lahore, PK

August 2004 to February 2005

- Acquired key clinical skills in a high patient turnover and case mix setting.
- Honed skills in appropriate diagnosis and management of acute medical problems and to create effective care plans following discharge.
- Rendered effective diabetes care during rotation at the diabetes clinic.
- Partook in weekly didactic, such as presentations and case discussions, to enrich the educational experience offered at the rounds.

#### **PRESENTATIONS**

- Pancreatic Trauma Talk, Department of General Surgery, Shaikh Zayed Federal Postgraduate Medical Institute, Lahore, September 2005.
- Mechanical Bowel Preparation versus No Preparation before Elective Left-Sided Colorectal Surgery

   Journal Club, Department of General Surgery, Shaikh Zayed Federal Postgraduate Medical Institute,
   Lahore, July 2005.
- Prophylaxis and Treatment of Deep Vein Thrombosis in General Surgery Journal Club, Department
  of General Surgery, Shaikh Zayed Federal Postgraduate Medical Institute, Lahore, July 2005.

### **RECOGNITIONS/ ACHIEVEMENTS**

- **Punjab Merit Scholarship 1999-2004**: This prestigious scholarship by the state covers expenses for the entire MBBS course and is awarded upon achieving a highly competitive merit demonstrated by scores on "state-wide entry test" and other examinations.
- Annual Confidential Reports/ Employment Evaluations: top 10%
- Quality Management: top 10%

#### PROFESSIONAL SOCIETIES

- Pakistan Medical and Dental Council (PM&DC)
  - Licensed for unsupervised practice everywhere in Pakistan
  - o License No.: 45466-P
- Saudi Commission for Health Specialties (SCHS)
  - o Licensed for unsupervised practice everywhere in Saudi Arabia
  - o Specialty: SCHS General Practice
  - o License No.: 13-R-M-0018139
- Educational Commission for Foreign Medical Graduates (ECFMG)
  - The ECFMG Certificate authorizes the use of the Doctor of Medicine "MD" Professional Doctorate title in United States
- Federation of State Medical Boards (FSMB)
  - o The Step 3 qualification leads to a license for practicing medicine in USA without supervision
- Australian Medical Council (AMC)
  - The AMC qualification leads to eligibility for license as a physician under supervision—a requirement for overseas doctors in Australia

#### **VOLUNTARY ACTIVITIES**

- Chohan Hospital Sundar, Giving community medical/surgical services from November 2014 till August 2015
- Jinnah Hospital Lahore, 6-months house physician job on basis of waiver of stipend
- **Field Officer; WHO Program for Polio Surveillance,** under WHO auspices, Community Department, Punjab Medical College, Faisalabad. 2002
- Field Officer; Polio Immunization Campaign, EPI 1999, Community Department, Quaid-e-Azam Medical College, Bahawalpur. 1999
- Pakistan Physiological Society (undergraduate research), Physiology Department, Punjab Medical College, Faisalabad. 1999 to 2000
- National Guard; National Cadet Corps and Women Guards, Pakistan. November 1995 to September 1996

#### **IT SKILLS**

- Adept in use of Computer/ Internet/ Software.
- Proficient in MS Word, Excel, OneNote and PowerPoint.
- Competent use of EMRs: OneNoteEMR<sup>©</sup> & Health Insights MedicaPlus<sup>®</sup>.

### **LINGUISTIC SKILLS**

- English: IELTS 7.0 (Academic), Speaking/Listening: 7.5
- Urdu/ Punjabi: Native
- Arabic: Working proficiency

References and Supporting Documentation to be furnished upon request

